this new wave of AI companies is is
growing revenue like just like actual
customer revenue, actual demand
translated through to dollars showing up
in bank accounts at like an absolutely
unprecedented takeoff rate. We're seeing
companies grow much faster. I'm very
skeptical that the form and shape of the
products that people are using today is
what they're going to be using in 5 or
10 years. I think things are going to
get much more sophisticated from here.
And so I think we probably have a long
way to go. These are trillion dollar
questions, not answers. But once
somebody proves that it's capable, it
seems to not be that hard for other
people to be able to catch up, even
people with far less resources. When a
company is confronted with fundamentally
open strategic or economic questions,
it's often a big problem. Companies like
need to answer these questions and if
they get the answers wrong, they're
really in trouble. Venture, we can bet
on multiple strategies at the same time.
We are aggressively investing behind
every strategy that we've identified
that we think has a plausible chance of
working. If you want to understand
people, there's basically two ways to
understand what people are doing and
thinking. One is to ask them and then
the other is to watch them. And what you
often see in many areas of human
activity, including politics and many
different aspects of society, the
answers that you get when you ask people
are very different than the answers that
you get when you watch them. If you run
a survey or a poll of what, for example,
American voters think about AI, it's
just like they're all in a total panic.
It's like, "Oh my god, this is terrible.
This is awful. It's going to kill all
the jobs. It's going to ruin
everything." If you watch the revealed
preferences, they're all using AI.
A lot of folks have sent questions ahead
of time and and what I what I've done is
kind of curated into a few different
sections uh in in an AMA this morning
with uh with Mark. So, what we thought
we'd do is cover uh four big topics. So,
AI and what's happening in the markets,
policy and regulation, um all things
816Z, and then we've got a a fun
catchall which we're we're calling
sandbox of things if we get to it. So,
starting first maybe with uh with the
biggest question. We're sitting in the
middle of the AI revolution. Mark, what
inning do you think we're in and and
what are you most excited about?
>> First of all, I I would say this is the
biggest tech technological revolution of
my life. Um and you know, hopefully I'll
see more like this in the next whatever
30 years, but I I mean this is the big
one. Um and just in terms of order of
magnitude, like this is clearly bigger
than the internet. Um like the the the
comps on this are things like the
microprocessor and the steam engine and
electricity. So that this is a really
this is a really big one. um the wheel.
Um the reason this is so big, I mean
maybe obvious to folks at this point,
but I'll just go through it quickly. So
um if you kind of trace all the way back
to the 1930s, uh there's a great book
called Rise of the Machines that kind of
goes through this. Um if you trace all
the way back to the 1930s, there was
actually a debate among the people who
actually invented the computer. Um and
it was this this sort of debate between
whether computer they kind of understood
the theory of computation before they
before they they actually built the
things. Um and um they they had this big
debate over whether the computer should
be basically built in the image of what
at the time were called adding machines
or calculating machines where you know
think of sort of essentially cash
registers. Um IBM is actually the
successor company to the national cash
register company uh of America. Um and
so like and and and that was of course
the path that the industry took which
was building these kind of hyper literal
you know mathematical machines you know
that could execute mathematical
operations billions of times per second
but of course had no ability to kind of
deal with human beings the way humans
like to be dealt with and so you know
couldn't understand you know human
speech human language um and so forth
and and that's the computer industry
that got built over the last 80 years
and that's the computer industry that's
built all the wealth of uh uh and and
financial returns of the computer
industry uh over the last 80 years you
know across all the generations of
computers from mainframes through to
smartphones. Um but but they knew at the
time they knew in the 30s actually they
understood the basic structure of the
human brain. They understood they had a
theory of sort of human cognition and
and and actually they had the theory of
neural networks. Um and so they they had
this theory that um the there's actually
the first neural network uh paper
academic paper was published in 1943 you
know which was over 80 years ago which
is extremely amazing. Um there's an
interview you can read an interview or
you can watch an interview on YouTube
with uh these two authors Makulla and
Pitts and you can watch an interview I
think with Makulla on YouTube from like
I don't know 1946 or something. He was
like on TV you know in the in the
ancient past and it's literally like
it's amazing interview because it's like
him in his beach house and for some
reason he's not wearing a shirt um and
he's like you know talking about like
this future in which computers are going
to be you know built on on the model of
a human brain through through neural
networks. Um and and that was the path
not taken. And basically what happened
was right the computer industry got
built in the in the image of of like the
adding machine. Um but and the neural
network basically didn't happen but the
neural network as an idea continued to
be explored in academia um and sort of
advanced research by sort of a rump you
know movement that was originally called
cybernetics and then became known as as
artificial intelligence uh basically for
the last 80 years and and and
essentially it didn't work like
essentially it was basically decade
after decade after decade of excessive
optimism uh followed by disappointment.
When I was in college in the 80s, there
had been a famous kind of AI boom bust
uh cycle in the 80s in venture and in
Silicon Valley. Um I mean it was tiny by
by modern standards, but it it at the
time was a big deal. Um and um you know
by the time I got to college in '89 um
in computer science departments, AI was
kind of a backwater field and everybody
kind of assumed that it was never going
to happen. But the scientists kept
working on it to their credit and they
they they built up this kind of enormous
reservoir of of concepts and ideas and
then basically we all saw what happened
with the CHIGPT uh moment. all of a
sudden it it sort of crystallized. It's
like oh my god, right? It turns out it
works. Um and and so you know that
that's the moment we're in now. And then
you know really significantly that was
what you that was less than three years
ago, right? That was the summer of 20 it
was the the Christmas of 22. So, we're
sort of three year we're we're sort of
three years in um to, you know,
basically what is effectively
effectively an 80-year revolution um of
actually being able to deliver on all
the promise that the that the people on
the all the on the alternate path, the
sort of human cognition model path, you
know, kind of saw from the very
beginning and and then, you know, the
great news with this technology is it's
already it's kind of ultra democratized.
you know, the best AI in the world is
available. Launch at GPD or Grock or
Gemini or or um you know, these other
you know, these other products that you
can just use um and you can just kind of
see how they work and you know, same
thing for video, you can see with Sora
and VO kind of state-of-the-art uh with
that you can see with music, you can see
you know uh Suno and IDO and so forth.
Um and so like you know we're basically
seeing that happen and now and now
Silicon Valley is responding with this
just like incredible rush of enthusiasm.
And you know, really critically this
gets to the magic of Silicon Valley,
which is, you know, Silicon Valley long
since has ceased to be a place where
people make silicon that, you know,
that's that not long ago moved out out
of the out out of California and then
ultimately out of the US, although we're
trying to bring it back now. Um but but
but the great kind of virtue of Silicon
Valley o over the last you know over the
last you know 80 years of its existence
is its ability to kind of uh recycle
talent from previous waves of technology
and new waves of technology uh and then
inspire an entire new generation of
talent you know to basically come join
the you know join the project. Um and so
Silicon Valley has this recurring
pattern of being able to reallocate
capital and talent and build enthusiasm
and build critical mass and build
funding support and build you know human
capital and build you know everything
enthusiasm um you know for each new wave
of technology. So, so that's what's
happening with AI. Um, you know, I I
think probably the biggest thing I could
just say is like I'm surprised I think
essentially on a daily basis of what I'm
seeing. Um, uh, and and you know, we
we're we're in the fortunate position to
kind of get to see it from from two
angles. Uh, you know, one one is we
track the underlying science and and,
uh, and kind of research work very
carefully. And so I would say like every
day I see a new AI research paper that
just like completely floores me um of
some new capability um or some new
discovery uh or some new development
that I that I would have never
anticipated that I I'm just like wow I
you know I can't believe this is
happening. And then um on the other side
of course you know we see the flow of
all of the new uh products uh and all
the new startups. Um and you know I
would say we're routinely um you know
kind of seeing things and again kind of
have my my jaw on the floor. Um, and so,
you know, it feels like we we we've
unlocked this giant vista. Um, I do
think it's going to kind of come in fits
and starts. Um, you know, the these
things are messy processes. Um, you
know, you know, this is an industry that
kind of routinely gets out over risks
and overpromises. Um, and and so, you
know, there, you know, there will
certainly be points where it's like,
wow, you know, this isn't working as
well as people thought, or you know,
wow, this turns out to be too expensive
and the economics don't work or
whatever. But, you know, against that, I
would just say the capabilities are
truly magical. And and by the way, I
think that's the experience that
consumers are having when they use it.
And I think that's the experience that
businesses are having for the most part
when they uh you know, when when they're
working on their pilots and and looking
at adoption and and and then and then it
translates to the underlying numbers. I
mean, we're we're just seeing a this new
wave of AI companies is is growing
revenue like just like actual customer
revenue, actual demand uh translated
through to dollars showing up in bank
accounts. Um you know, at like an
absolutely unprecedented takeoff rate.
We're seeing companies grow much faster.
um uh you the the key leading AI
companies and the companies that have
real breakthroughs um and have real have
very compelling products are growing
revenues that you know kind of faster
than any any way I've certainly ever
seen before. Um and so like just just
from all that it kind of feels like it
has to be early. Like it it's kind of
hard to imagine that we've like we we've
topped out in any way. It feels like
everything is still developing. I mean
quite frankly it feels like the products
to me it feels like the products are
still super early. Like I'm I'm I'm very
skeptical that the form and shape of the
products that people are using today is
what they're going to be using in five
or 10 years. I think I think things are
going to get much more sophisticated
from here. Um and so I think we probably
have a long way to go.
>> Maybe on that that topic. So one of the
big knocks is yes the revenue is immense
but the expenses seem to also be keeping
pace. So like what are people missing as
a part of that discussion and topic?
>> Yeah. So just start with just like core
business models, right? Um and so you're
right. There's basically this industry
basically has two two core business
models. consumer business model and the
quote unquote enterprise uh or
infrastructure business model. Um you
know look on the on the consumer side we
we just live in a very interesting world
now where where the internet exists and
is fully deployed right. Um, and so I'll
give you an example. Sometimes people
ask us like, "Is AI like the internet
revolution?" It's like, well, a little
bit, but like the thing with the
internet was we had to build the
internet. Like we we like we had we had
to actually build the network and we
actually had to, you know, and
ultimately it involved enormous amount
of fiber in the ground and it involved
enormous numbers of like mobile cell
towers and, you know, enormous number
of, you know, shipments of of of
smartphones and tablets and and and
laptops in order to get people on the
internet. Like there was this like just
like incredible physical lift um, you
know, to do that. And and by the way,
people forget how long that took. Uh
right, the the the you know, the
internet itself is a invention of the
1960s, 1970s. Um the consumer internet,
you know, was a new phenomenon in the
early '90s. Um but, you know, we didn't
really get broadband to the home until
the 2000s. You know, that really didn't
start rolling out actually until after
the com crash, which is fairly amazing.
And then we didn't get mobile broadband
until like 2010. And and people actually
forget the original iPhone dropped in
2007. It didn't have broadband. it was
on a it was on a narrowband 2G network.
Um it did not have high speed like it
did not have anything resembling
high-speed data. Um and so it wasn't
really until you know really about 15
years ago that we even had mobile
broadband. So so the internet was this
massive lift but but the internet got
built right and smartphones
proliferated. And so the point is now
you have 5 billion people on planet
earth that are on some version of you
know mobile broadband internet right um
and you know smartphones all over the
world are selling for you know as little
as like 10 bucks. Um and you know you
have these you know amazing projects
like geo and India that are bringing you
know you know the sort of the remaining
you know kind of the remaining
population of of planet earth that
hasn't been online until now is coming
online. So, you know, so we're talking
five billion, six billion, you know,
people and and then the consumer, the
reason I go through that is the consumer
AI products could basically deploy to
all of those people basically as quickly
as they want to adopt, right? Um, and so
sort of the internet's the carrier wave
for AI to be able to proliferate at kind
of light speed uh uh into the broad base
of the global population. And and that's
a let's just say that's a potential rate
of proliferation of a new technology
that's just far faster than has ever
been possible before. Like what you
know, like you couldn't download
electricity, right? you you couldn't
download, you know, you couldn't
download indoor plumbing. Um, you know,
you couldn't download television, but
you can download AI. Um, and and and
this is what we're seeing, which is the
AI consumer, you know, the AI consumer
killer applications are growing at at at
an incredible rate. Um, and then and
then they're monetizing really well. Um,
and and again, you know, we we I
mentioned this already, but like
generally speaking, the monetization is
is very good. Um, by the way, including
at higher price points. Um, one of the
things I like about the um, you know,
about watching the AI wave is the AI
companies I think are are more creative
on pricing than the SAS companies and
the consumer internet companies were.
And so it's it's for example now
becoming routine to have $200 or $300 t
per month tiers uh, for consumer AI
which I which I think is very positive
because I I think the I think a lot of
companies cap their kind of opportunity
by by capping their pricing uh, kind of
too low and I think the AI companies are
more willing to push that which I think
is good. So anyway, so that you know I
think that's reason for like I would say
you know considerable rational optimism
for the scope of of consumer revenues
that we're going to be talking about
here. And then on the enterprise side,
you know, there the question is
basically just, you know, what is
intelligence worth, right? Um, and you
know, if you have the ability to like
inject more intelligence into your
business and you have the ability to do,
you know, even the most prosaic things
like raise your customer service scores,
uh, you know, increase upsells, um, uh,
you know, or reduce churn or if you have
the ability to, um, you know, run
marketing campaigns more effectively,
um, you know, all of which AI is
directly relevant to, like, you know,
these are like direct business payoffs,
um, you know, that people are seeing
already. Um, and then if you have the
opportunity to infuse AI into new
products and all of a sudden, you know,
all of a sudden your car talks to you,
um, and everything in the world kind of
lights up and starts to get really
smart. Um, you know, you know, what's
that worth? And and again there you just
you you kind of observe it and you're
like, wow, the the leading AI
infrastructure companies are growing
revenues incredibly quickly. Um, you
know, the pull is really tremendous. Um,
and so, you know, again there it's just
it feels like this just like incredible
uh, you know, product market fit. Um and
and and the core business model, right,
is is is actually quite quite
interesting. The core business model is
is is basically is basically tokens by
the drink, right? And so it's it's sort
of tokens of intelligence uh you know,
per dollar. And oh, and then by the way,
this is the other fun thing is if you
look at what's happening with uh the
price of AI, the price of AI is falling
much faster than Moore's law. And when I
could go through that in great detail,
but basically like all of the inputs
into AI on a perunit basis, the costs
are collapsing. Um and and and and then
as a consequence there's kind of this
hyperdelation of per unit cost and then
that is like driving you know just like
you know a more than corresponding level
of demand growth you know with with with
elasticity. Um and so you know even
there we're like it feels like we're
just at the very beginning of kind of
you know figuring out exactly how you
know expensive or cheap this stuff is
getting. I mean look there's just no
question tokens by the drink are going
to get a lot cheaper from here. Um
that's just going to drive I think
enormous demand. Um and then everything
in the cost structure is going to get
optimized right? Um and so you know when
when people talk about like you know the
chips or you know whatever you know kind
of the unit input costs for building AI
you know you now have these like m the
losses of blind demand are are going to
are going to kick in right um what's the
you know in any market that has sort of
commodity like characteristics you know
the number one cause of a of a of of a
glut is a shortage and the number one
cause of a shortage is the glut right um
and so you have you know to the extent
you have like shortage of GPUs or
shortage of whatever infest chips or
shortage of you know whatever data
center case, you know, if you look at
just the history of humanity building
things in response to demand, you know,
if there's a shortage of something that
can be physically replicated, it it does
get replicated. Um, and so there's going
to be like just enormous build out of
all I mean there is there's just
hundreds of billions or at this point
trillions of dollars maybe going into
the ground um in all these things. And
so the the per unit cost of the AI
companies are going to drop like a rock
um you know over the course of the next
decade. Um and so like I yeah I mean the
economic questions of course are very
real and of course there's you know
microeconomic questions around around
all these businesses but the the sort of
macro forces have been at least here I
think are very strong um and and yeah I
I just given the underlying value of the
of of this technology to both the
consumers the enterprise users. Um, and
given the just like incredibly
aggressive discovery that's happening of
of all the ways that people can use this
in their lives and in their businesses,
like it's just it's really hard for me
to see how it both doesn't grow a lot
and generate just enormous revenue.
>> Yeah. And actually, I think it was like
two or three weeks ago where AWS was
saying like the the GPUs that they've
been using, they've been able to extend
back to even like seven plus years. So
like the shelf life also of the GPUs
that they're using is now extending in
ways of which they can optimize better
than maybe perhaps the last couple of of
cycles. as well. Is that the right way
to think about it as well?
>> Yeah, that's right. And then and then
that's one that's that's one really
important question and observation and
and then by the way that also gets to
this other kind of question um where
there's different theories on it. Um
which is basically big models versus
small models.
>> Um and so a a lot of the data a lot of
the data center build is oriented around
hosting um training and and and and
serving the the big the big models, you
know, for for all the obvious reasons.
Um but there's also the small the small
model revolution is happening at the
same time and and and and if you just
kind of track you know you can get get
the various research firms have these
charts you can get um but if you just
kind of track the if you track the
capability of the leading edge models
over time what you find is after 6 or 12
months there's a small model that's just
as capable um and so there there there's
this kind of chase function that's
happening which is the capabilities of
the big models are basically being
shrunk shrunk down uh and provided at at
at at smaller size and then therefore
smaller cost you know quite quickly. So,
I I'll just give you the the most recent
example that just got hit over the last
two weeks. And again, this is a thing
that's just kind of shocking. Um is
there's this Chinese company that has a
um well, I forget the name of the
company, but it's it's uh the company
that produces the model called Kimmy,
which is spelled Kim Mi, which is one of
the leading open source models out of
China. Um and uh the new version of
Kimmy is a reasoning model that is at
least according to the benchmark so far
is basically a replication of the
reasoning capabilities of GPT5, right?
and and and these new models of GPT5
were a big advance over GPT4 and of
course GPT5 costs a tremendous amount of
money to to develop and to serve and all
of a sudden you know here we are
whatever 6 months later and you have an
open source model called Kimmy and I
think I don't know if they had it's
either shrunk down to be able to run on
either it's like one MacBook or two
MacBooks um right um and so you can all
of a sudden if you have like an applica
you if you're a business and you want to
have a reasoning model that's GPT5
capable um but you you know you're
whatever you're not going to pay the
whatever GPT5 cost or you're not going
to want to have it be hosted and you
want to run it locally, um, you know,
you can do that. Um, and and and again,
that's just like another just it's just
like another, you know, it's another
breakthrough. Like it's just it's
another another Tuesday, another huge
advance. It's like, oh my god. And then
of course, it's like, all right, well,
what is OpenAI going to do? Well,
obviously they're going to go to GPT6,
right? Uh, and you know, right? And so
there there's this kind of lattering
that's happening where the entire
industry is moving forward. Um, the big
models are getting more capable. The
small models are kind of chasing them.
Um uh and then um and then the small
models provide you know completely
different way to deploy um you know at
at at at very low price points. Um and
so yeah I think and and you know we'll
we'll see what happens. I mean there
there are some very smart people in the
industry who think that ultimately
everything only runs in the big models
because obviously the big models are
always going to be the smartest and so
therefore you're always you know you're
always going to want the most
intelligent thing because why would you
ever want something that's not the most
intelligent thing for any application.
You know the counterargument is just
there's a huge number of tasks that take
place in the economy and in the world
that don't require Einstein. you know,
where, you know, where, you know, 120 IQ
person is great. You don't need a, you
know, 160 IQ, you know, PhD in, you
know, string theory. You just like have
somebody who's competent and capable and
it's great. Um, and so, you know, I I,
you know, and I we've talked about this
before. I tend to think the AI industry
is going to be structured a lot like the
computer industry ended up getting
structured, which is you're going to
have a small handful of basically the
equivalent of supercomputers, which are
these like giant, you know, kind of we
call god models that are, you know,
running in these giant data centers. Um
and then and then you know I I I I I'm
not like convinced on this but my my
kind of working assumption is what
happens is then you have this cascade
down of smaller models all ultimately
all the way the very small models that
run on embedded systems right run on run
on individual chips inside every you
know physical item in the world. Um and
that you know the smartest models will
always be at the top but the volume of
models will actually be the smaller
models that proliferate out and right
that's what happened with microchips. uh
it's what happened with computers which
became microchips and then it's what
happened with operating systems and with
with a lot of everything else that we
built in software. Um so you know I tend
to think that's what will happen. Um
just quickly on the chip side um again
like chips you if you look at the entire
history of the chip industry uh uh
shortages become gluts um and you get
just you know like anytime there's a
giant profit pool in a in a new chip
category um you know somebody has a lead
for a while and kind of gets you know um
let's say the the the profits
appropriate to what we u what we call
robust market share um but in time what
happens right is that that draws
competition and of course you know that
that that's happening right now. So
Nvidia's, you know, Nvidia is an
absolutely fantastic company, fully
deserves the position that they're in,
fully deserves the profits that they're
generating, but they're now so valuable,
generating so many profits that it's the
bat signal of all time to the rest of
the chip industry to figure out how to
advance the state-of-the-art AI chips.
Um, and that's, by the way, and that's
already happening, right? And so you've
got other major companies like AMD
coming at them, and then you've got
really significantly, you've got the
hyperscalers building their own chips.
Um, and so, you know, a bunch of the big
a bunch of those kind of big tech
companies are building their own ships.
Um, and of course then the Chinese are
building their own ships as well. Um and
so it's just it's like pretty likely in
5 years that that you know AI chips will
be you know cheap and plentiful at least
in comparison to the situation today. Uh
which again I think will you know will
tend to be extremely positive for the
economics of of the kinds of companies
that we invest in.
>> Yep. And that startups are also starting
to go after new chip design as well
which is exciting.
>> Yeah. Well, that's the other thing is
yeah, you have these disruptive startups
and actually that just for a moment on
the chips, they were not really big
investors in chips because it's kind of
a big it's kind of a big company thing,
but um it's a little bit of historical
happen stance that AI is running on
quote unquote GPUs um you know which GPU
stands for graphical processing unit. So
um and basically just for people who
haven't tracked this there were
basically two kinds of chips that made
the personal computer happen. the
so-called CPU central processing unit
which classically was the Intel x86 x86
chip that's kind of the brain of the
computer and then there was this other
kind of chip called the GPU or graphical
processing unit that was the sort of
second chip in every PC that does all
the graphics um and you know and this is
graphics you know 3D graphics for gaming
or for CAD CAM or for you know anything
else you know Photoshop or for anything
that involves you know lots of visuals
and so the the kind of canonical
architecture for a personal computer was
a CPU and a GPU by the way same thing
for smartphones um but by the way. And
over time, you know, these have kind of
merged and so like a lot of CPUs now
have GPU capability built in. Actually,
a lot of GPUs now have CPU capability
built in. So this, you know, this has
gotten fuzzy over time, but like that
that was like the classic breakdown. But
the fact that that was the classic
breakdown, you know, kind of meant that
while Intel had a you know, monopoly for
a long time on CPUs, um there was this
other market of GPUs which Nvidia um you
know basically fought the GPU wars for
30 years and and and came out the winner
like what was the best company in the
space. But it was like a hyper
competitive market for graphics
processors. it was actually not that
high margin and it was actually not that
big. And then basically it just it
turned out that there were two other um
forms of computation that were
incredibly valuable that happened to be
massively parallel uh in how they
operate which which happened to be very
good fits for the GPU architecture. And
those two basically highly lucrative
additional applications were
cryptocurrency starting about you know
15 years ago and then AI starting about
you know whatever four years ago. Um,
and so and and Nvidia like I would say
very cleverly set itself up with an
architecture that works very well for
this, but it's also just a little bit of
a twist of fate that it just turns out
that if AI is the killer app, it just
turns out that the GPU architecture is
the best legacy architecture is devoted
to it. And I go through that to say like
if you were designing AI chips from
scratch today, you wouldn't build a full
GPU. you would build dedicated AI chips
that were much more much more
specifically adapted to AI um and would
have I I think would just be much more
economically efficient and you know John
to your point there there there are
startups that are actually building
entirely new kinds of chips uh oriented
specifically for AI and you know we'll
have to see what happens there you know
it's hard to build a new chip company
from scratch um you know it's possible
that one or more of those startups makes
it on their own um and some of them are
you know doing very well um it's also
possible of course that they get bought
um you know by big companies that that
have the ability to scale them. Um, and
so, you know, you know, we'll see
exactly how that unfolds. Um, and of
course, we'll also, by the way, see, you
know, the Koreans are going to play here
for sure. Um, uh, the Japanese are going
to play. Um, and then, you know, the
Chinese in a major way, uh, as well.
And, you know, they have their own, you
know, native chip ecosystem that they're
that they're building up. And so there
there there there are going to be many
choices of AI chips in the future. Um,
and it's going to be that, you know,
that'll be a giant battle that'll be a
giant battle that we observe very
carefully. um and that we uh make sure
that our our companies basically are
able to take full advantage of.
>> While while on the topic of of
international um we you mentioned Kimmy
earlier. So it seems like some of the
best open source models today are from
China. Should this be worrisome to to
folks? How are you thinking and talking
about this topic with with folks in DC?
I know you were just there last week.
How much of this is a concern for uh US
companies particularly just having seen
the rise of China do unnatural things in
solar markets, car markets? Um are they
kind of flooding the ecosystem so that
they can eventually kind of take share
and and increasingly uh own the the
ecosystem?
>> Yeah. So uh you know a couple things. So
one is you know you know you want to
start these discussions by just kind of
saying like you know look there's
there's vigorous debate in in the US and
around the world of look like you know
how much are we in a new cold war with
China you know and exactly like how
hostile you know should should we view
them and it you know it's very tempting
by the way it's very tempting and I
think it's a very good case made that
we're in like a new cold war that's like
that in a lot of ways is like the US
versus USSR um in the in the 20th
century um you know it is the counter
argument would be it is more complicated
than that because the US and the USSR
were never really intertwined from a
trade standpoint Um and and a big part
of that quite frankly was the USSR never
really made anything that anybody else
needed I guess other than weapons. Um
but like you know the USSR's primary
exports were literally like you know
literally like wheat and and oil. Um
whereas of course China exports just a
tremendous number of physical things
right um including like a huge part of
like the entire supply chain of parts
that basically go into everything that
American manufacturers you know kind of
make right and so by the time a US you
know whatever by the time an American
company brings a toy to market right or
a uh you know or a car um or anything or
a computer or a smartphone or whatever
like it's got a lot of componentry in it
that was made in China so there so there
is a much tighter in interlinkage
between the the American and Chinese
economies than there as the American and
Soviet economies and you know may maybe
you know Adam Smith or whatever might
say you know that's good news for peace
and that you know both countries need
each other by the way the other part of
that argument is that the Chinese
basically the Chinese you know the
Chinese governance model is based on
high employment um you know because you
know if if if you know at least all the
geopolitical people say if China ended
up with like 25 or 50% unemployment that
would cause civil unrest which is the
one thing that the CCP doesn't want and
so the corresponding part of the trade
pressure is China needs the American
export market you know the American
consumer is like a third of the global
economy. Uh a third of global consumer
demand. Um and so you know China needs
the US export market or it has high all
of a sudden a lot of its factories would
go kind of instantly bankrupt and you
know would cause mass unemployment and
unrest in China. So so anyway like you
know we there is this complicated it's a
it's a complicated intertwined um
relationship. Um having said that you
know the the mood in DC basically for
the last 10 years on a bipartisan basis
um has been that we need to take we the
US need to take China more seriously as
a geopolitical foe. And you know under
under under that school of thought
there's sort of the sort of you know
there's there's the military dimension
which is you know the sort of the you
know the the risk of some kind of war in
the South China Sea the risk of some
kind of war around around Taiwan and so
that you know that that has everybody in
Washington on high alert um you know
there's also this this economic question
around the kind of de-industrialization
of the US potential re-industrialization
and what that means about you know
dependence on China and then and then
there's and then there's this this this
AI question um and and the AI question
is an economic question but It's also
like a geopolitical question which is
okay you know basically AI is
essentially only being built in the US
and in China. Um you know the rest of
the world either you know can't build it
or doesn't want to which which we could
talk about. So it's basically US versus
China. Um and then AI is going to
proliferate all over the world and is it
going to be American AI that
proliferates all over the world or is it
going to be Chinese AI that proliferates
all over the world and so and I was
saying just generally across party lines
in DC this you know the the things I
just went through are kind of how they
look at it. Um and and the Chinese are
in the game and so the you know the
Chinese are in the game for sure you
know with software u you know deepseek
you know was kind of the big you know
kind of fire the starting gun in the
software race and now you've got I think
it's I think you've got four it's like
deepsek uh which is a deep so deepseek
is an AI model from actually a hedge
fund um in uh in China um it's a little
bit uh kind of took a lot of people by
surprise um then Quen is the model from
Alibaba. Kimmy is from another startup.
Oh, called Moonshot. The company's
called Moonshot. Um, and then there's,
you know, and then, um, you know,
there's also Tencent and BU. Um, and,
um, by Dance, um, you know, that are all
primary, you know, companies doing a lot
of work in AI. Um, and so, you know,
there's somewhere between three to six,
you know, kind of primary AI companies.
And then there's, you know, tremendous
numbers of of startups. Um, and so, you
know, they're in the race on on, uh, you
know, they're in the race on on on
software. Um, they are, you know,
working to catch up on chips. They're
not there yet, but they're working
incredibly hard to catch up. And just as
an example of that, you know, the at
least the common understanding um you
know, in the US is that the reason you
haven't seen the new version of DeepSeek
yet is that basically the Chinese
government has instructed them to build
it only on Chinese chips um as a as a
motivator to get the Chinese chip
ecosystem up and running. Um and and
then the main chip company there is
Huawei, although there could be more in
the future. Um and then there's um so
you know, so so so there's that and then
and then there's everything to follow
which is basically AI in kind of robotic
form, right? And so there there's this
basically global technological economic
robotics competition that's kicking off.
Um and u you know China kind of starts
out ahead on robotics because they're
just ahead on so many of the so many of
the components that go into robots u
because the you know the sort of like I
said this the kind of entire supply
chain of like electromechanical things
you know basically moved from the US to
China 30 years ago and and has never
come back. So so so that's kind of the
the the the DC lens on it. Um and and I
would say you know DC is watching it uh
you know quite carefully. Um uh the the
the the big kind of supernova moment
this year was the deepseek release. The
deepseek release was surprising on a
number of fronts. Um one was just how
good it was and again along this line of
it took the capability set that were
running in large models in the cloud and
kind of shrunk it um onto a um you know
into into a uh into a a sort of a a
reduced size you know a smaller version
of sort of equivalent capabilities that
you could run on small amounts of local
hardware. Um and so there was that and
then it was also a surprise that it was
released as open source uh and
particularly open source from China
because China China does not have a long
history of open source. Um and then um
it was also a surprise um that it
actually came from a hedge fund. Um so
it didn't come from a big R&D you know
sort of university research lab. It
didn't come from a you know from a big
tech company. it it came from a hedge
fund and it it like as as far as we can
tell it it basically is this somewhat
idiosyncratic situation where you just
have this incredibly successful quant
hedge fund with all these you know super
geniuses um and the the founder of that
hedge fund you know basically decided to
build AI um and you know at least
external indications are this was a
surprise to even even the Chinese
government it's it's impossible to prove
you know what the Chinese government was
surprised by or not but you know there's
at least the atmospherics are that this
was not exactly planned this was not a
national champion tech company at the
time that Deepseek was released it was
it sort of came out of left field which
by the way is very encouraging for the
field that it was possible for somebody
to do that kind of who was unknown right
because it kind of means that maybe you
don't need all these you know super
genius superstar researchers maybe
actually smart kids can just build this
stuff which I think is is the direction
things are headed um and so that kicked
off I would say like this kind of I I
don't know copycat's the wrong word but
that that was sort of it feels like the
success of deepseek and the success of
deepseek from China as open source kind
of kicked off a sort of trend in China
releasing these open source models um
you know Look, the cynics, you know, in
DC would say, you know, yeah, like
they're dumping, right? The the they're
obviously dumping. They're trying to,
you know, they see that the West has
this opportunity to build this China
industry. You know, they're trying to
commoditize it right out of the gate.
You know, there's probably something to
that. Um, you know, the the Chinese
industrial economy does have a history
of, you know, sort of, let's say,
subsidized production that leads to
selling, you know, selling things below
cost in some cases. Um, but I think also
it's it like I think that's almost too
cynical of a view also because it's just
like all right wow like they're really
in the race like open source closed
source whatever like that you know
they're actually really in the race. Um,
you know, we we've talked in the past, I
think, on on on LP calls about, you
know, these policy fights that, you
know, we've been having in DC for the
last two years. And, you know, there was
a big pretty pretty big push within the
US government, you know, two years ago
to basically, you know, restrict, uh,
you know, or outright ban, you know, a
lot of AI. Um, and, you know, it's very
easy for a country that is the only game
in town to have those conversations.
It's quite another thing if you're
actually in a foot race with China. Um,
and so I think actually the the the the
policy landscape in DC has I would say
has improved dramatically as a
consequence of sort of an awareness now
that this is actually a two- horse race,
not a one-horse race.
>> For sure. Yeah. Actually on on the point
I'll I'll jump ahead here to policy and
regulation just because it seems like uh
the current stance on on 50 different
set of AI laws by state seems like a
catastrophic
uh way to to put us effectively with a
uh or one of our our hands tied behind
our our back here in terms of the the AI
race. What's a state of plan on that?
Are folks recognizing that that would be
catastrophic for progress and
development? Where do most people at
least stand on that topic today?
Yeah. So it's a little bit complicated.
So I'll rewind to say like two years ago
I was very worried about like really
ruinous federal federal legislation on
AI and there was there was we you know
we engaged you know kind of very heavily
at that point which we've talked about
in the past and I think the good news on
that is I think the risk of that sitting
here today is very low. Um I there's
very little mood in DC on either side of
the aisle uh to really you know
essentially there's very little there's
very little interest in doing anything
that would prevent us from beating
China. Um so so you know on the federal
side things things are much better now.
There there will there will be issues
and there are tensions in the system but
like things are looking looking pretty
good. Um that has translated Jen to your
point that's translated a lot of the
attention to the states and basically
what's happened is you know under our
system of of federalism uh you know the
states get to pass their own laws on a
lot of things. Um and so uh yeah,
basically you know a lot of you know and
and you know with these things it's
always a combination. A lot of
well-meaning people are trying to figure
out what to do at the state level and
then of course there's a lot of
opportunism where AI is just the hot
topic. And so if you're a you know
aggressive up and cominging state
legislator or whatever in some state and
you want to run for governor and then
president you know you want to kind of
attach yourself to the heat. Um and so
there's like a political motivation to
to do state level stuff. Um yeah and
sitting here today like we're tracking
on the order of,200 bills across the 50
states. And by the way, um, not just the
blue states, also the red states. Um,
and so, you know, I'm I've, you know,
for the last like 5 years or whatever, I
spent a lot of time complaining about,
uh, you know, kind of what Democratic
politicians are threatening to do to
attack. There's also a lot of
Republicans, like Republicans are not a
block on this. And there are quite a few
like local Republican officials in
different states, um, that that also, I
think, have, you know, let's say, you
know, misinformed or ill-advised, um,
views and are trying to put together,
uh, put out bad bills. um you know it's
a little bit weird that this is
happening and that you know the federal
government does have regulation of
interstate commerce um and you know
technology AI kind of by definition is
interstate like you know there's there's
no AI company that just operates in
California or just operates in you know
Colorado or Texas um you know AI of all
technologies AI is obviously something
this this sort of national in scope um
you know it's sort it's sort of obvious
that the federal government should be
the regulator not not not the states um
but but the federal government need
needs to assert itself needs to step in.
There there was actually an attempt to
do that. There was a um there was an
attempt to add a moratorium of state
level AI regulation that basically would
would reserve the right of the federal
government to regulate AI and sort of
prevent the states from moving forward
with these bills. That was I think part
of the negotiation for the quote one big
beautiful bill and then that that there
was a deal behind that and that deal
kind of blew up at the at the last
minute and that moratorium didn't happen
and and you know in fairness the critics
of that moratorum it probably was a was
it was probably too much of a stretch.
Well, it was I'm sorry. It was
definitely too much of a stretch to get
enough support to pass, but it was also
probably too much of a stretch in terms
of restricting the states from certain
kinds of regulation that they really
should be able to do. So, so it just it
didn't quite come together. Um, there's
a very active we're having very active
discussions in DC right now about kind
of the next, you know, the kind of the
next turn on that. Um, you know, the
administration is I would say the
administration is very supportive of of
the idea of of the federal government
being in charge of this as part of it
being an actual, you know, 50-st state
issue. Um, and and and an issue of
national importance. Um, and then, you
know, I'd say most most Congress people
on both sides of the aisle, you know,
kind of get this. Um, so we just we we
kind of have to figure out a way to, you
know, to land this, but but I think
that'll happen. Um, some of the state
level bills are wild. Um, the the
Colorado passed a very draconian uh
regulation bill uh last year. Um, and
against like furious objections from the
local startup ecosystem in in in around
Denver and Boulder. Um, and actually
they're they're now actually trying to
reverse their way out of that bill. um
you know a year later some of the the
nuance of it like the algorithmic
discrimination and like how to mitigate
like what were some of the the extreme
versions of what they they had proposed.
>> Yeah. So the really draconian one was
the the one that we really fought hard
was the one in California which was
called SB1047 and it wasn't it it it was
basically it was modeled basically after
the was called the EU AI act. So the
European Union's AI act. Okay. And this
is the backdrop to all the US stuff
which is the EU passed this bill called
the AI act I don't know whatever two
years ago and it basically has killed AI
development in well it's actually killed
AI development in Europe to a large
extent. Um and then it even it it's so
draconian that even even big American
companies like Apple and Meta are not
launching leading edge AI capabilities
in their products in Europe. Like that
that's how that's how like draconian
that bill was. And it's it's sort of a
classic it's a classic kind of European
thing where they like you know like they
just thought that you know they they
have this kind of view that it's just
like well you know we if we can't be the
leader they literally say this by the
way if we can't be the leaders in
innovation at least we can be the
leaders in regulation. Um and and and
then they pass this like incredibly you
know kind of ruinous uh selfharm you
know kind of thing and then you know a
few years pass and they're like oh my
god what have we done and so they're you
know they're kind of going through their
own version of that. Um, by the way, you
know, I I you know, when I talk about
Europe, I I tend to be very dark about
the whole thing. I will tell you the
darkest people I know about Europe are
the European entrepreneurs who moved to
the US. Um, are just like absolutely
furious about what's happening in in in
Europe on this stuff. Um, but but even
there, like it it's it's so bad in
Europe, like they they shot themselves
in the foot so badly that there's
actually a process now at the at the EU
to try to unwind that. They're trying to
unwind the GDPR. So u anyway for people
tracking Europe uh Mario Draghi um is
the former I guess prime minister of
Italy did this thing about a year ago
called the Draghy report which is the
report on European competitiveness and
he kind of outlined kind of in great
detail all the ways that Europe was
holding itself back and part of it was
overregulation areas like AI. So so
they're trying to reverse out of that or
making gestures you know we'll we'll see
what happens. Um
it in the middle of all that, California
sort of inexplicably decided to
basically copycat the EU AI act and try
to apply it to California. Um which
might strike you as completely insane.
To which I would say yes, welcome to
California. Um uh and um you know, it
was this basically this like Sacramento
political dynamic that kind of got got
crazy. Um it would have you know
completely killed you know AI
development in California. Um
unfortunately our governor vetoed it at
the last minute. Um it did pass both
houses legislature that he vetoed at the
last minute. Um it to Jen to your point
it would have done for it would have
done a whole bunch of things that were
ruinously uh bad. But one of the things
it would have done is it would have
assigned downstream liability um uh to
open source developers. Um and so you
know we talked about you know this
Chinese open source thing. Okay so you
got Chinese out there with open source.
Now you're gonna have American companies
that have open source AI. And by the way
you're also going to have American
academics and just like independent
people in their nights and weekends
developing open source. um you know
which is a key way that all this
technology proliferates and and so this
this law would have assigned downstream
liability to any misuse of open source
to the original developer of the open
source and so you know you're an
independent developer or you're an
academic or you're a startup you develop
and release an AI model the AI model
works fine the day you release it it's
great but like 5 years later it gets
built into a nuclear power plant and
then there's a meltdown of the nuclear
power plant and then somebody says oh
it's the fault of the AI um the the the
the legal liability for that nuclear
meltdown or for anything any other
practical real world thing that would
follow in the out years would then be
assigned back to that open source
developer. Of course, this is completely
insane. It would completely kill open
source. It would completely kill
startups doing open source. It would
completely kill academic research like
in its entirety. Um, you know, anything
in the field. Um, and so, you know, that
like that's the level of playing with
fire. Um, you know, kind of that these
state level politicians have become
enamored with. Um, like I said, I think
the good news is the feds understand
this. I suspect that this is going to
get resolved, but it but it does need to
get resolved because, you know, just as
a country, it just doesn't make any
sense to let let the states kind of
operate suicidally like this. Um, and so
that's what we're doing. You know, we we
talk about this, we call this our little
tech agenda. Um, we're extremely focused
on on on the freedom and starters
innovate. We are not trying to argue,
you know, many many other issues. We
operate in a completely bipartisan
fashion. We have extensive um support,
you know, on both sides of the aisle and
for both sides of the aisle. Um, so it's
it's a truly bipartisan effort. um very
policy based and you know I think very
much aligned with the interests of the
country uh broadly um and so that is
what we're doing and then and then the
other question we get we we get actually
you know in some cases from LP but in a
lot of cases actually from employees um
is like okay why us right like you know
you know with with any sort of you know
policy question like this there's always
this collective action question which is
just like you know tragedy of the
commons which is in theory like
everybody every venture firm every tech
company whatever should be weighing in
on these things in practice what happens
is mo most them just simply don't. Um,
and so at some point it falls on
somebody's shoulders to fight these
things. And we we we Ben and I just
basically concluded that the stakes here
were just way too high. You know, if if
we're going to be the industry leader,
we just have to take responsibility for
our own destiny. You know, for better or
for worse, I think that's the cost of
doing business uh for being the leader
in the field right now.
>> Before we get off the topic of of AI, I
want to go back to one question that
that was submitted in. So, do you think
usage based or utility is a right way to
price an AI compared to seeds?
Ah that is a fantastic question. So this
is one of these giant this is in my my
list of what I call the trillion dollar
questions u where you know depending on
how this is answered will drive you know
trillions of dollars of market value. So
yeah so usage based pricing it's it's
actually
it's actually fairly amazing if you
think about this from a startup
standpoint from a venture standpoint
it's actually fairly amazing what's
happened and I'm trying I'm not really
talking about this in public because I
don't really I because I don't want it
to stop. I think it's actually quite
amazing. Um, which is you have these
technology companies, you know, these
big tech companies with these like
incredible R&D capabilities that are
building these big models, these big AI
models with this incredible, you know,
new new kind of new new kind of
intelligence. And then it it turns out
that they were already in a war. They
were already in the cloud war, right?
And so they were already in the war for
kind of cloud services. And this is like
AWS versus Azure versus uh Google Cloud.
Um, you know, and then all the all these
other all these other cloud efforts. And
so what what what what actually happened
was they sort of like there's an
alternate universe in which they
basically just kept all of their magic
AI secret and captive and just used it
in their own business um or used it to
just compete with more companies um you
know in more in more categories but
instead what they've done is they've
basically you know if I commod
commoditize is too strong a word but
they they have they have proliferated
their magic new technology through their
cloud business um which is which is this
business that just has these like
incredible scale you know kind of kind
of components to But um you know and
sort of this hyper competition between
the providers and these you know these
these prices that that come down very
fast. Um, and so you've got like the
most magic new technology in the world
and then it's basically being served up
by those companies in in in a as a cloud
business and made made basically
available to everybody on the planet to
just click and use and for like
relatively small amounts of money and
then on on a usage basis which means and
usage is great for startups because you
it means you can start easily right you
the the the you know there's very you
know there's basically no fixed co for a
startup building an AI app they don't
have giant fixed cost because they could
just tap into the open AI or anthropic
or Google or Microsoft or whatever you
know cloud you know tokens by the you
know, intelligence tokens by the drink
offering and just get going. Um, and so
it's it's kind of this this from this
from the startup standpoint, it's like
this marvelous thing where like the most
magical thing in the world is available
by the drink. You know, it's absolutely
amazing. Um, uh, I, you know, and, you
know, that model, you know, by the way,
that model's working and those companies
are happy and they're growing really
fast and they're, you know, happily
reporting massive cloud revenue growth
and, you know, they they're happy with
the margins and so forth and so, you
know, I think generally it's working.
Um, and those businesses are, I think,
likely to get much larger. Um and so I
think you know generally that's going to
work but but to to to the question like
that doesn't mean that the optimal
pricing model for for example all of the
applications should be tokens by the
drink and in fact very much I think not
the case. Um you know we spend a lot of
time working we actually have you know
dedicated you know experts on on pricing
in our firm. We spend a lot of time with
our companies working on pricing because
it's you know it's really this magical
art and science that that a lot of
companies don't take don't take
seriously enough. So we spend a lot of
time with other companies on this. And
of course, you know, a core principle of
pricing is you don't want to price by
cost if you can avoid it. You want to
price by value, right? Like you want to
price you price where you're getting a
percentage of the business value um of,
you know, especially when you're selling
two businesses, you want to price as a
percentage of the business value that
you're getting. And so so you do have
some AI startups that are that are
pricing by the drink for certain things
that they're doing, but you have many
others that are exploring other pricing
models. uh you know some that are just
like replications of SAS pricing models
but you also have other companies are
explor exploring pricing models for
example of well if the AI can actually
do the job of a coder or the AI could do
the job of a doctor or a nurse or a
radiologist or a lawyer or a parallegal
right or whatever or a teacher. Um you
know basically can you can could can you
price by value and can you get a
percentage of the value of what of what
of of of what otherwise would would
would have been you know would have been
literally a person. um you know or or by
the way equivalently can you price by
marginal productivity. So if you can
take a human doctor and make them much
more productive because you give them
AI, you know, can you price as a
percentage of kind of the productivity
uplift, uh, you know, from the from from
the from the augment, you know, the comb
symbiotic relationship between the the
human being and and the AI. Um, and so I
I think what we see in startup land is
like a lot of experimentation happening
on on these pricing models. And I and I
and I think again I I think that's like
super healthy. Um, I I you know, I was
in this little speech on this is like
high prices are really underappreciated.
High prices are often a favorite of the
customer. It's actually really funny. A
lot of like the naive view on pricing is
the lower the price, the better it is
for the customer. The the more
sophisticated looking at it is higher
prices are often good for the customer
because a higher price means that the
vendor can make the product better
faster, right? Like you can actually
companies with higher prices, higher
margins can actually invest more in R&D
and they can actually make the product
better. Um and you know most people who
buy things aren't just looking for the
cheapest price. They want something
that's really that's going to work
really well. Um and so often high
prices, you know, the customer doesn't
ever say this. it'll never show up in a
survey. Um, but but the high price can
actually be a gift for the customer
because it can make the vendor better,
can make the product better, and
ultimately make the customer better off.
And so I I'm I'm very encouraged by the
degree to which the AI entrepreneurs are
willing to run these experiments. And I,
you know, we'll have to see where it
pans out. But at least so far, I feel I
feel good about the the uh, you know, at
least the attitude of the industry about
it.
>> Awesome. I actually uh I was, as you
were gone through, I had probably 10
more follow-up questions, but I'm
actually going to go back to um a topic
you had uh briefly, the trillion dollar
questions. Will open source or close
source win? Feels like we we've come out
on this this debate or where do you
where do you put that?
>> No, I think this is still open. I I
think this is still very open. Um you
know that like the the the closed source
models keep getting better. Um uh by the
way if you generally if you just like
take the temperature of the people
working at the big labs who work on the
big proprietary models like generally
what they'll tell you is progress is
continuing at a very rapid pace. Um you
know there's there's this you know
there's this periodic concern that kind
of shows up on online which is or in the
in the market which is like you know
maybe the capabilities these models are
topping out um and you know there's
certain there's there's certain areas in
which you know there's there's you know
people are working but like the people
working at the big labs are like oh no
we have like 800 new idea like we have
tons of new ideas we have tons of new
ways of doing things. We we might need
to find new ways to scale but like we we
have a lot of ideas on how to do that.
We know a lot of ways to make these
things better and you know we're
basically making new discoveries all the
time. So like I would say you know
generally the people working in the like
across all the big labs are are pretty
optimistic. Um and so like I I think the
big models are going to continue to get
better you know very quickly here and
then you know overall um and then the
open source models continue to get
better. Um and like I said you know you
know every every every I don't know
every month or something there's like
another big release of like something
like this Kimmy thing. Um where it's
just like wow like you know that's
amazing and you know wow they really
like shrunk that down and got that
capability on a very small form factor.
Um uh and so um yeah that's the case and
then you know I maybe just the third
kind of thing to bring up is um the
other really nice benefit of open source
um is that uh open source is the thing
that's easy to learn from right um and
so if you're a you know computer sc if
you're a computer science professor who
wants to teach a class on on CS on AI or
if you're a computer science student
that's trying to learn about it or if
you're just like a normal engineer in a
normal company trying to learn this new
thing um or just somebody in your you
know by the way somebody in basement at
night with a startup idea. Um the
existence of these of these
state-of-the-art open source models is
amazing because that's the education
that you need. Like they actually these
open source models actually show you how
to do everything. Um right. Um and so
like and and what that's leading to
right is the proliferation of the
knowledge about how to build AI is like
expanding very fast. Um again as
compared to a counterfactual world in
which it was all basically bottled up in
two or three big companies. And so, you
know, the open source thing is also just
proliferating knowledge and then that
knowledge is generating a lot of new
people. Um, and so I I you know, you
know, as you guys have all seen sitting
here today, AI researchers are at an
enormous premium. You know, AI
researchers today are getting paid more
than professional athletes. Um, right?
Like, you know, and that's right, that's
a supply demand imbalance there. There
aren't enough of them to go around. But,
you know, again, shortages create glut.
um the the number of the number of smart
people in the world who are coming up to
speed very quickly on how to build these
things u I mean some of the best AI
people in the world are like 22 23 24
like they you know kind of by definition
they haven't been in the field that long
you know you know they they can't have
been experts their whole lives right so
you know they they kind of have to have
come up to speed over the course of the
last four or five years and and if if
they if they've been able to do that
then then there's going to be a lot more
in the future that are going to do that
um and so just the the the sort of
spread of the level of expertise on this
technology is happening now very quickly
Um, so I yeah, I mean I think it's still
like I said, I think it's I think it's
still a race. And and by the way, you
know, look, the long-term answer may
well just be both. Um, you know, like I
said, if you if you believe my pyramid
industry structure, then there will then
there will certainly be a large business
of whatever is the smartest thing almost
regardless of how of how much it costs.
Um, and then there but there will also
be this just giant volume market of of
smaller models everywhere, which which
is what we're also seeing.
>> Yep. Yep. The another question you had
posed at at that point in time was will
incumbents versus startups went and at
that point in time I think there was a
mixed bag of where the incumbents were
approaching AI. I think that's radically
changed in the last two years. Um and
then on the counter example the the
blossoming of startups increasingly now
maybe migrating into the incumbent
category just how big they since that
time. You you want to take that uh
question and and give uh your assessment
of where where the state of the world
is?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, I mean, look, you know,
big companies that are definitely, you
know, playing hard. You know, Google's
playing hard. Meta's playing hard. Um,
Amazon, um, Microsoft, um, you know,
there's a bunch of these companies that
are, you know, that are kind of in in in
there, um, you know, very aggressively.
And then you've got these, you know,
what we call the new incumbents like
Anthropic and and, uh, and Open AI. Um,
but you also have like, you know, even
in the last two years, you've had this
birth of all of a sudden like brand new
companies that are almost instant
incumbents. And you, you could say XAI
is one of those. Uh, ML, by the way, ML
is the great outlier to my Europe thing
from earlier. like Mald is actually
doing very well as sort of the European
kind of uh you know French national
European uh continental you know kind of
AI champion um sort of the you know the
exception that proves the rule um but
you know there's there's a bunch of
these now that are like you know doing
quite well and are kind of becoming new
incumbents um and then of course there's
tons of startups by the way there's and
then there's there's actual foundation
model startups right and so you know we
funded uh you know we funded Ilas out of
open AAI to do a new foundation model
company we funded Miriam Maratti also
out of open AI we funded Faith Ali out
of Stanford to do a world
foundation model company and so you know
there you know there's there are new
swings all all you know all early but
very promising um for to kind of build
you know new incumbents quickly um and
so you know that's all happening and
then and then you know what and then on
top of that there's just this giant
explosion of AI application companies
right and so there there's basically
companies that then usually startups
that basically take the technology and
then you know field it in a specific
domain whether that's law or medicine or
education or you know creativity um or
or or or whatever Um but again here it's
just like it's amazing kind of how how
sophisticated things are getting very
quickly. So
talk about the application companies for
a moment. So like an application company
like classic example is like a cursor is
like an application company. So they
take the core AI capability which they
purchase by the drink from you know
anthropic or open AI or Google um you
know to tokens by the drink and then
they they they build a code basically a
code editor what we used to call an IDE
um integrated development environment or
basically like a a software creation
system um so they build like an AI
coding system um on on top of the
anthropic or open AAI or whatever you
know kind of kind of big models feel
that and that the the critique of those
companies in the industry has been oh
those are what are called called GPT
rappers is kind of the pjorative And the
idea basically being is well they're not
actually like they're not actually doing
anything that's going to preserve value
because the the actual the the whole
point of what they're doing is they're
surfacing AI but it's not their AI. The
the AI that's being surfaced is from
somebody else. And so these are kind of
these pass pass through shell things
that ultimately won't have value. It
actually turns out what's happening is
kind of the opposite of that which is
the the leading uh AI application
companies like Cursor I mean f first of
all what they're discovering is they
they're not just using a single AI
model. they're actually they actually as
these products get more sophisticated
they actually end up using many
different kinds of models that are kind
of customtailored to the specific
aspects of how these products work. Um
and so they may start out using one
model but they end up using a dozen
models and then in the fullness of time
it might be 50 or 100 different models
for different aspects of the product. A
and then B they end up building a lot of
their own models. Um and so they they a
lot of these the leading edge
application companies are actually
backward integrating and actually
building their own AI models because
because they have the deepest
understanding of their domain. and
they're able to build the model that's
best suited to that. Um, and then by the
way, also AI open source, they're also
able to pick up and run an open source
models. Um, and so if they don't like
the economics of of buying intelligence,
you know, by the drink from a from a
from a cloud service provider, you know,
they can pick up one of these open
source models and implement it instead,
which, you know, which these companies
are also doing. Um, and so the the best
of the best of the AI application
companies are they are actually
full-fledged deep technology companies
actually building their own AI. Um and
so that you know that's I think
>> small models though right Mark when you
think about god models versus small
models as you were describing that but
that would be small would you categorize
that as a small
>> well some of them I mean we I will let
them I will let them announce you know
whatever they're doing whenever it's
appropriate but some of them are now
also doing big model development um and
again this this is also part of what
this is also part of the learning just
in the last two years well so like
here's a big learning just from the last
two years which is very interesting
which is two years ago or three years
ago for sure you would have said wow
open AI is like way out ahead um and
like it's probably going to be
impossible for anybody to catch up and
then it's like okay well Anthropic
caught up and so but you know they came
out of open AI and so they had all the
secrets you know whatever and so knew
how to do it and so okay they caught up
but surely nobody can catch up after
them and then very quickly after that
there were a raft of other companies
that caught up very fast and and XAI is
maybe the best example of that which is
like you know XAI you know Elon's
company XAI is the company name gro is
the consumer product version of it um
XAI basically caught up to you know
state-of-the-art openai anthropic level
in in like less than 12 months from a
standing start right and So, and again
that that kind of argues against any
kind of permanent lead, right, by by any
one incumbent that's just going to
basically be able to lock the entire
market down like if you can catch up
like that. And then and then as we as
we've discussed the you know the China
part is all new in the last year, right?
The deepseek uh this the deepseek moment
I think was in January or February of
this year, right? So less than 12 months
ago. Um and so and now you've got like
four Chinese companies that have
effectively caught up. And so, you know,
so it's like, all right, I mean, again,
this is these are these are trillion
dollar questions, not answers. But it's
just like, wow, okay, like it's one of
these things where once somebody proves
that it's capable, it seems to not be
that hard for other people to be able to
catch up, even people with far less
resources. Um, and so, you know, I don't
know what that does. Maybe it makes you
slightly more skeptical in the long run
economics of of the big players. On the
other hand, maybe it makes you like more
bullish about the startup ecosystem. Uh,
it certainly should make you more
bullish about uh startup application
companies, right? being able to do
interesting things, which is why we're
so excited about that. Um, you know, it
should make you probably, you know, a
bit more excited about about certainly
about China. Um,
on the other hand, the Chinese
competition putting pressure on the
American system to not screw itself up
is very positive. So, it should probably
make you a little bit more bullish on
the US. Um, and so, yeah, I think, you
know, the these are, yeah, these are
yeah, these are are live dynamics and I
I think we still need more time to pass
before we know the exact answer. I
should say this, but sometime because
sometimes I don't sometimes I freak
people out when I say these are open
questions. Um, when a company is
confronted with fundamentally open
strategic or economic questions, it's
often a big problem because a company
needs to have a strategy and the
strategy needs to be very specific. Um,
and a company has to make like very
specific concrete choices about where it
like deploys investment dollars and
personnel and like the strategy has to
be like logical and coherent or the
company kind of collapses into chaos.
And so like companies like need to
answer these questions and if they get
the answers wrong, they're really in
trouble. Um, venture We have our issues
and venture but a huge advantage that we
have is we don't have to we we can bet
on multiple strategies at the same time
right um and and we are doing this so we
are betting on big models and small
models and prepared train models and
open source models right and and you
know and foundation models and
applications right uh and consumer and
enterprise and so the portfolio approach
the nature of it is like we we are
aggressively basically uh we we are
aggressively investing behind every
strategy that we've identified that we
think has a plausible chance of
even when that even when that's
contradictory to another strategy that
we're investing in and one is just like
the world's messy and probably a bunch
of things are going to work and so like
there's not going to be clean yes or no
answers to a bunch of this like a lot a
lot of the answers to this I think are
just going to be and answers but the
other is like if one of these strategies
doesn't work like you know we're not
we're not trying to hedge per se but you
know we're going to have representation
in the portfolio of the alternate
strategy and and so we're going to have
mult multiple ways to win. So anyway,
that's that's the goal. That's the
theory of why we are, you know, kind of
taking the approach in the space that
we're taking. Um, and that's why I have
a big smile on my face when I say that
there are these big open questions
because I think that actually works to
our advantage.
>> It's a good seg uh to A16Z questions
because we we've gotten a few in so far
and and uh we had a few that uh were
were sent in ahead as well. So uh I'll
start one with a with a broad topic.
What is something you and Ben disagree
and commit on?
disagree commit. Um, you know, we agree.
I mean, we we Ben I was going to say,
you know, we're an old married couple,
so we argue argue constantly, but we've
been
>> where the romance is dead.
>> The romance is long dead. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes. The light the fire the fire has
long since gone out. Um, but um uh yes,
if you Yes. We're in the park squabbling
all the time. Um so, um yeah, I mean, so
look, we debate everything. We we argue
about everything. We that that said like
you know one of the things that's made
our partnership work is like we do we do
tend to come to the same conclusion like
each of us is open to being persuaded by
the other one and so we we end up coming
you know we end up coming to the same
conclusion most of the time. Um so I
would say there there aren't like a
there aren't I said specifically sitting
here today there are like zero issues
where I'm sitting here and I'm like I
can't believe you know I just I can't
believe I'm you know I'm putting up with
this crazy thing on on his on his part
that he's doing um that I really
disagree with but I feel like I have to
commit to or I I don't think vice versa.
Um and so so we don't have any of those.
Um, you know, quite honestly, the
biggest thing I say the biggest thing
that I that he and I the biggest thing
that he and I discuss, this this by the
way, this is not this is not the most
important thing we're doing, but it is a
topic since somebody asked the question.
The biggest thing he and I discuss where
I I don't know, maybe I'm always like
second guessing myself or I I I never
quite know where I should come out on it
that he and I talk about a lot is just
like basically the public footprint of
the company. Um so like our pres our
presence in the our presence in the
world in terms of like public statements
uh controversy um uh you know uh how we
vocalize and express our views on things
um and I would just say there like you
know there's a real there's a tension
there's a real it's you know maybe
obvious but like a very important
tension like generally speaking the more
out there we are and the more outspoken
we are and the more controversial we are
the better for the better for the
business in the sense of the
entrepreneurs love it. Uh the the the
founders want to work with is very clear
at this point. The founders want to work
with uh uh people who basically are
brave and controversial and take
controversial stands uh and articulate
things clearly and and they want that
for a bunch of reasons. One is because
it's a demonstration of courage which
they appreciate. But the other is
because it it it it teaches them who we
are before they even meet us. Um and and
and that has just proven to be just like
this incredible competitive advantage.
you know, long long-term LPs will know
like this is why we started with a very
active marketing strategy from the very
beginning and like it completely worked.
Like the the whole thing was if we're
able to broadcast our message and we're
able to basically be very clear in what
we believe even to the point where it's
controversial, like the best founders in
the world are going to understand us
before they even walk in the door,
right? And they're going to they're
going to know us even before they've met
us as opposed to everybody else in
venture, at least at the time, that was
basically just like keeping everything
quiet. Um where they, you know, the
founder just has no idea who these
people are and what they believe. And so
that that like worked incredibly well.
It continues to work incredibly well. Um
it's by the way it's you know it's
generally true across the industry. It's
it's it's like generally the case. On
the other hand, there are externalities
to being you know publicly visible and
and and and to being controversial um on
many fronts. Um we are I would say this
we are we're very much we're trying very
hard to thread this needle. So like
we're we're not backing off of generally
being a a company that does a lot of
outbound. we, you know, we Eric
Worenberg and the team that he's built,
you know, that we've talked to you guys
about in the past, um, you know, is I is
already off to the races. Um, you know,
we're we're going to, you know, we're
tripling down on the idea of basically
being the leaders and articulating the
tech and business issues that matter.
You know, the, you know, the issues for
sure that people need to be able to
understand. Um, and and that's proven to
be very effective. By the way, a fair
amount of our coms are actually aimed at
Washington. Um because again it's like
if you're a policy maker in Washington
and you're sitting there 3,000 mi away
and your entire information source is
like East Coast newspapers that hate
Silicon Valley. Like that's bad. Um and
so you know our ability to like
broadcast, you know, inform points of
view on technology. We just we meet
people in DC all the time um who say,
"Yeah, I you know, most of what I know
about this topic I learned from you guys
because I listened to the podcast, I
read the articles, I watched the YouTube
channel." Um and so, you know, we're
we're going to continue to do that. And
so we, you know, over over over overall
we have a, you know, we're kind of on
our front foot on that stuff. But yeah,
he he and I do he and I do go back and
forth a bit on exactly how, yeah, how
many third rail topics should we touch?
Um, and uh and how frequently. And I I
would say we're we're we are trying to
we are trying to moderate that.
>> As Elizabeth Taylor said, as long as I
spell our name right, um, it's
oftentimes could be good in most
scenarios, particularly when it comes to
little tech. uh double uh and also I
think embedded in that question is
probably uh some degree of of uh uh the
relationship that you and Ben have which
is now going on 30 plus years at this
point. Uh so much so that that Mark has
become uh one person representing both
uh some people refer to Mark as Andre
and Horowitz no lost the mark have
combined just into one person. Uh
>> yes
>> that's the result of 30 plus years
working together. Okay. Um, so it's been
2 years since you've reorganized around
AI, launched AD. What do you think you
got most right? Uh, and in hindsight, is
there anything that you underestimated
or or missed in that decisioning
process?
>> No, I mean, look, we made we made plenty
of mistakes. I think those were I think
those were the right calls. I mean, AI
was like I said, like you know, the
whole theor back up the whole theory of
venture the whole theory of venture that
we've had from the beginning is that you
know, many people before us have had as
well. that's very correct I think is the
whole theory is like the money adventure
is made when there's like a a
fundamental architecture shift like when
there's like a fundamental change in the
technology landscape. Um and and that's
been true for you know adventure
basically forever. Um uh and and the
reason is because if you have a
fundamental change in technology then
you have this period of creativity in
which you can have basically aggressive
you know very aggressive kind of people
you know kind of start these new
companies and and they have this kind of
shot to kind of come in and you kind of
win categories before big companies can
respond. um if there's no fundamental
change in technology, it's very hard to
make startups work because the big
companies just end up doing everything.
And so you so venture kind of, you know,
sort of lives or dies on on the basis of
these of these waves of these
transitions. Um and and so there's
always there there's always this
question. It's always this question. I
mean, I would just say the best venture
capital firms in history, I I think are
the ones that were the most aggressive
at being able to navigate from wave to
wave, right? And and and look, I was a
beneficiary of this when I came to
Silicon Valley in ' 904. you know that
there was no venture firm in 1994 that
was like the internet venture capital
firm like that it just didn't exist. Um,
but there were a set of venture capital
firms at the time, you know, at the time
our our firm Kleiner Perkins that said,
"Oh, this is a new architecture. This is
a new technology change. It seems
totally crazy. Everybody says you can't
make money on it. Whatever, whatever.
These kids are nuts." But like, we're
going to make those bets. Um, and so
they were willing to invest. And by the
way, you know, KP in the in the in the
'90s invested not only in us, but also
in Amazon and then Google and like in,
you know, company after company after
company. They invested in at home, which
basically made made home broadband work.
um you know they invested in in a fleet
of companies and they were a venture
capital firm that had started in the
1970s around really around what was at
the time called Minicomputers which was
like a you know three generations of
techn technology back and they had
navigated from wave to wave um and and
you know the same thing is true for
Sequoia the same thing is true for
basically any successful venture firm
has been in business for you know 30 or
40 or 50 years and so I I think in this
business like of all businesses like you
you just you need you need to get onto
the new thing um you know it it was I
mean quite honestly it was I pretty
amazing that most of the venture
ecosystem just decided to sit crypto
out. Um and and the number of VCs that
we talked to between call it, you know,
the release of the Bitcoin white paper
in 2009 to the beginning of the crypto
war in 2021 who just basically said,
"Oh, we're not going to do crypto." It
was fairly it's I I like I don't I I
never quite know what to do with the VC
who says, "Oh, there's a new wave of
technology and I'm very deliberately not
going to participate in it." And I'm
always like like, "Is that not the job?"
Right? Like so so so like I was fairly
amazed by the VCs that didn't make the
jump uh to crypto. You know they they
looked briefly smart during the crypto
wars I would say of the last you know
three or four years and I think they
they probably look maybe a little bit
less smart now. Um you know AI is
another one of these where there are
certain firms that are are jumping all
over it and there are certain firms that
are just kind of sitting back and
letting it happen. Um and um and and by
the way there were certain firms that
never made it to the internet. I mean
there were there were firms that were
very well known in the 80s um and very
successful that just like did not make
the jump uh to the internet and
basically just petered out. And so
anyway long-winded way of saying I think
I think in this business of all
businesses you have to jump you have to
jump on the new wave. Um and I and I
think we got the magnitude of it of it
right that this is like a fundamental
fundamental transformation inside the
firm. Um you know AD is you know AD is
doing great. Um AD AD itself I believe
is also a beneficiary of AI. um right
because in in two ways one is a lot of
the kinds of products that AD companies
build themselves benefit from AI and
then also AI is a driver of demand in
other sectors of AD like like energy and
materials. Um and so I you know I think
that that generally is is very
consistent and you know is working well.
Um by the way you know crypto's back
back to being a you know I would say an
exciting industry as a consequence of
all the policy changes. Um and then and
then there's even going to be I think
intersections. I I think there's
actually going to be quite a few
intersections between AI and crypto. Um
and then and then biote you know biotech
also bio and healthcare I think are
obviously going to be transformed by AI
both on the healthcare side and on the
actual drug discovery side and you know
and that's underway. And so any anyway
so like the the the individual efforts
in the firm feel good um and suitable
for the time the inter the interactions
between the teams um and the kind the
the hybrid ideas you know the companies
that are coming at these things from
multiple angles uh you know feels really
good um you know maybe the correlarying
question is like you know what do we
feel like we're missing right now um and
I I think the answer is really not like
I don't I don't think like right now
we're not missing a vertical like I I
don't like as of right now like there
there's not like a specific vertical of
like I don't know whatever that like
where we just like, oh, we just need,
you know, we need the equivalent of a
new of a new unit or the equivalent of a
new um you know, new fund or whatever. I
don't I don't see that at the moment. I
think it's more executing extremely well
in the verticals that we have in front
of us. Um and um and then, you know,
being the best possible partner to the
to the portfolio companies.
>> Yeah. Actually, on the point of of AD,
um because uh AI is creating and there's
a lot of talk around AI taking jobs,
etc. Ironically enough, the jobs in AD
sectors have never been more in demand
in the physical world related to energy,
related obviously to data center build,
etc. So like the the pendulum it seems
like also is uh is swinging from just an
accelerant standpoint from from a
society uh point of view. Um you talked
about the importance of society also
needing to be ready for tech adoption.
Like have you seen that accelerating of
recently? what's your sentiment of of
how to actually um increase that just to
also make sure the convergence of of
adoption also falls in line with with
how quickly tech is is actually being
implemented.
>> Yeah. So, you know, look, we've talked
about this before, but um you know,
look, for a very long time, tech was
just not a very relevant look, if you go
back over like whatever 300 years, like
there's just like recurring waves of
like total panic and freakout caused by
new technology. Or even you go back 500
years, you go back to the printing
press, you know, which basically was
handin-hand with the the sort of
creation of Protest Pro Protestantism,
which really changed things. Um, and
then um, you know, you you go back to
um, you know, there there were just
always kind of, you know, continuous
panics there. You know, there have been
m there have been multiple ways of
automation panics for the last 200
years. You know, a lot of the
foundational panic under Marxism was
basically a fear of of of of the
elimination of jobs through the
application of automation. um uh you
know a lot of the same arguments you
hear today about like AI is going to
centralize all the wealth in a handful
of a few people and everybody else is
going to be poor and emiserated like
that that basically is what Markx used
to say um which I think was by the way
wrong then is wrong now we can talk
about but um you know and then even like
in the 1960s there was this whole panic
around around AI um uh replacing all the
jobs there was this there's this great
uh it's long long forgotten but it was a
big deal at the time during the Johnson
administration you read these AI pause
letters today you know that this one
that just came out a few weeks ago that
Prince Harry uh headlined of all people.
Um and um uh uh you know he talks about
AI is going to ruin everything and it's
like and 1964 there was basically a
group of like the leading lights in
academia science and uh you know um kind
of public affairs that there was this
thing called the triple committee or the
committee for the triple revolution. If
you do a Google search on it's like
committee for the triple revolution
Johnson white house or whatever you'll
this thing will pop up. Um and you know
it was a very similar kind of manifesto
of like we need to stop the march of
technology today or we're going to ruin
everything. Um and and then you know
even in the course of the last 20 years
there was like a big panic around um
actually outsourcing in the 2000s was
going to take all the jobs and then it
was actually robots weirdly enough in
the 2010s which is amazing because
robots didn't even work in the 2010s and
they kind of you know still don't. Um
but uh you know there's a panic around
that and now there's kind of whatever
level of AI panic. Um and so like you
know I would just say like look that you
know the way I would describe it is you
know we in Silicon Valley have always
wanted the work that we do to matter. Um
you know we spend most of our time quite
honestly with people telling us that
everything that we're doing is stupid
and won't work. Um like that's the
default position. Um you know and then
basically that flips at some point into
panic about how it's going to ruin
everything. Um you know it's it's easy
sitting out here to be cynical about
that. Um especially when you kind of see
the patterns over time. I you know my
view is we need to be actually very
respectful of that and we need to be
very aware of that and and basically
that we you know I use the metaphor with
the dog that caught the bus like we
always wanted to work on things that
matter we are working on things that
matter uh people in the rest of society
actually really do care about these
things um and you know and it's our
responsibility to think that all through
very carefully and to do a good job um
you know both not just building the
technology but also explaining it you
know look you know I think we have a
real obligation to uh you know to to
really explain ourselves and engage on
these issues um in terms of how to
measure how going you know it's it's
sort of the classic social science
question um uh which is like okay if you
want to understand basically you know
patterns of people there's basically two
ways to understand what people are doing
and thinking um one is to ask them and
and then the other is to watch them um
and like every social every social
scientist like every sociologist will
will will will tell you this which
basically is you can you can ask people
right and and the way you do that right
is like you know surveys focus groups
polls um you know what they think Um but
then but then you can watch them and you
can do what's you know called reveal
preferences. They're just observe
behavior which is you can actually watch
their behavior and and and what you
often see in many areas of human
activity including politics and many
different aspects of society and culture
over time is the answers that you get
when you ask people are very different
than the answers that you get when you
watch them. Um and the reason is because
like I mean you could have a bunch of
theories as to why this is the Marxists
claim that people have false
consciousness. the the the the somewhat
the explanation I believe is just people
have opinions on all kinds of things
particularly when they're in a context
where they get to express themselves um
and they'll have a tendency to kind of
express themselves in very heated ways
and then if you just watch their
behavior they're often a lot calmer um
and a lot more measured and a lot more
rational in in what they do and so the
AI that's playing out in AI right now
which is if you pull if you run a survey
or a poll of what for example American
voters think about AI it's just like
they're all in a total panic it's like
oh my god this is terrible this is awful
it's going to kill all the jobs it's
going to ruin thing. The whole thing, if
you watch the revealed preferences,
they're all using AI. So, they're like,
they're downloading the apps. They're
using chat GPT in their job. They're,
you know, having an argument. You You
see this online all the time now. I'm
having an argument with my boyfriend or
girlfriend. I don't understand what's
happening. I take the text exchange. I
cut and paste it into chat GPT and I
have chat GPT explain to me what my
partner is thinking and tell me how I
should answer so that he's, you know, he
or she is not mad at me anymore, right?
So, or like, you know, I have this
thing, you know, I have a skin, you
know, I have a skin condition and
doctors, you know, da da da, and I take
a photo and I and I'm finally like
learning about my own health or I use it
in my job like I, you know, I had to get
this report ready for Monday morning and
I ran out of time and like it, you know,
chat GPT really saved my bacon. Um, and
so people in their daily lives are I
would, you know, just you just look at
the just look at the data you just like
they are not only using this technology,
they love this technology. Um, and they
love it and they're adopting as fast as
they possibly can. So I I tend to think
we're going to the public discussion of
this is going to ping pong back and
forth for a while because there is this
divergence between what people are
saying what people are doing. Um but but
I do think that the what people are
doing part is is is obviously the part
the part ultimately that wins and and
and I think this by the way I think this
technology is going to be exactly the
same as every other one. Um which is the
thing that's going to happen here is
this is just going to proliferate really
broadly. It's going to freak everybody
out and then you know 20 years from now
everybody's going to be like oh thank
god we've got it. Like wouldn't life be
miserable if we didn't have this? um and
or you know 5 years from now or or one
year from now you know people are going
to reach that conclusion. Um so I'm I'm
very optimistic about where this lands.
It's just that you know there will be
turbulence along the way.
>> I'm I'm smiling because I also witnessed
that in the wild. Literally late last
week I was on the plane. The guy next to
me was talking to his chat. I could see
him and he was like help me draft an
escalation letter to United for the
delay on this flight. I was like sir you
are on the flight right now. Like at
least wait until it's over.
It was very good though. I'm sure he had
a great email crafted as a as a part of
that. Uh so, okay, I'm going to switch
gears to uh a few fun questions that
that were sent in uh that uh is intended
to be a lightning round. So, so uh what
what is something you've changed your
mind on recently? Bonus points if it was
someone younger than you.
>> I mean, it's like every day. Um it's
just like it's just a constant, you
know, it's it's almost all like what's
in the realm of the possible. Um, I I'm
I'm terrible at specific examples, so I
don't I don't have one like ready at
hand, but like like I said, it's just
it's it's always Yeah. No, it's it's
often somebody showing up. It's either
something somebody writes or something
somebody says. Um, and yeah, it's almost
Yeah, it's very frequently somebody
who's very young. Um, and um, yeah, it's
just like I would say it's a it's a
routine experience.
>> Good way to stay young. Um, do you plan,
speaking of young, do you plan to be
cryogenically frozen?
Not with current not with current
cryogenic technology. Um the uh the the
the track record of that is not great.
Um uh and um the stories are somewhat
horrifying, but uh you know, we'll see.
>> We'll see. You got we still got some
time.
>> Um how do you stay grounded when your
influence itself may distort reality
around you?
>> Yeah. So
I was just say the good news, you know,
I would say the good news on several
front. So one is look the concern is
real. Um, and it's hard for me to it's
hard for me to talk about with sort of
my Midwestern, you know, kind of, you
know, Midwesterners, we we either are
very humble or we we're really good at
faking it, but um, uh, you know, it's
hard to talk about, but requires some
introspection. But yeah, I mean, look,
the the reality warping effect is
definitely real. Um, by the way, there
is a very big advantage to the reality
warping effect, um, which is being able
to get people to do what you want them
to do. Um, so that, you know, there is
there is another side to it. Um but it
you know it is a concern in terms of
like having an actual accurate
understanding of what's happening. I
guess I would say two things. I would
say one is um you know I mean one is
just you know my partners I think are
quite you know including Ben are quite
forthright um in telling me when I'm
wrong but you know more generally like
we're just we are very exposed to
reality. Um and so and this and again
you know you mentioned I don't know it's
a way to stay younger, make sure their
hair never grows back or whatever. It's
just like you know we run these
experiments you know cuz we make these
decisions about whether to invest or not
invest and we work with these companies
and all their things and like you know
reality kicks in quickly. You know the
the the delusions don't last very long
in this business. Um because like you
know these these things either work or
they don't. Um and you know you have
these like long elaborate you know
discussions about you know theories on
this and that and the other thing and
then reality just like completely smacks
you square in the face you know like you
idiot right you know like you know what
were you you like you know this is like
the you know the ultimate frustration of
the business which is also very
motivating which is the number of times
that you think that you've applied
superior analysis and then you've either
invested or not invested based on that
analysis and it turns out it was just
you the analysis was just completely
wrong right um and you know you just
like completely overrated your ability
to epistemically you know kind of
analyze these things you just you know
basically inflicted harm like I always
the question is always you know it's
sort of you know any activity that we do
is it value add or is it actually value
subtract right and and and I think in
this business of all businesses is kind
of like that and and that applies to all
of my own contributions as well so so
there is that and then and then I would
say um you know maybe the final thing is
just like I do have the entire internet
ready to tell me that I'm an idiot so
that also
that also doesn't doesn't hurt and it
and it does on a regular basis
on on the point of uh your alluding to
earlier about uh decisions on investing
in companies. My favorite line I think
it was from the uh the Cheeky Point
interview that you did uh was you know
when you invest in a company it doesn't
go well at least it goes bankrupt right
if it does if it does well and it does
fantastically well you hear about it
every single day
>> for the rest of your life. Yeah. For the
next for the next 30 years.
validity smacking you in the face saying
you fool.
>> You had it. It's literally It's
literally you had it in your office. All
you had to do is say yes.
And by the way, and this is the thing
like every great VC like if you this is
this is the stories that you know the
VCs tell each other. Every great VC
basically has this history of like my
god I had it was in my office. The thing
was in my office and I said no and if I
had just said yes. Um and so it's yeah
it's very hard to um yes the constant
reminders in the Wall Street Journal and
on CNBC every day that you made a giant
mistake um is yes very good very good
for the the old humility factor.
>> Yeah very humbling helps you stay
grounded uh all the time. Uh last
question do you plan to go to Mars if
and when that opportunity presents
itself?
>> Probably
not.
>> My subliminal Zoom background wasn't uh
sending the positive vibes. This is what
it
>> Well, I'm not even willing to leave
California. Um,
so I'm barely willing to leave my house.
So, um, uh, yeah, I may maybe by maybe
by VR.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, and then we'll see what happens. I
mean, look, having said that, I think
Elon's going to pull it off. Um, and so
I think, you know, I don't know. I don't
know. I don't want to predict. This is
not a prediction, but I, you know, I
would not be surprised if within a
decade there's routine trips back and
forth. Um, so, uh, yeah, we may, uh,
this this may actually become a a
practical question. And and by the way,
I do know a lot of people who are
probably going to go,
>> myself included. Put me on that.
>> Oh, fantastic.
>> The the flights around the world have
prepared me for the six-month journey to
Mars, so I will be just fine.